{
  "reference_number": "11548",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "As it is important for their to be an overarching law to hold government beholden too."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The most ambitious target: reducing total greenhouse gases to net zero by 2050. I also support taking a science-based approach to\n\n ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as impactful as possible: we should aim for negative levels of long-lived gases, while\n reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines its long-term certainty. However, the\n ability to revise the 2050 target in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements should be permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "yes - I agree with 5-year budgets set 10-15 years in advance, so that 3 are in effect at all times. This needs to be done so what ever\n government is in charge it is ensured every effort is made to reach targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "No - emissions budgets should not be altered in response to “economic changes” as this undermines their long-term certainty.\n\n However, the ability to revise budgets in light of major changes in scientific understanding or international agreements should be\n permitted."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The environment is too important to gamble on."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\n\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - we must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. This is of high importance to reflect Te Tiriti as we as a current nation are only\nguardians of the land and it is integral that we ensure it is protected for the preservation of our indigenous nga tangata history."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - the Commission should not be a decision-making body. However, the Government should be legally required to consider and\n\nformally respond to the Commission’s advice, and to provide an explanation if they do not act on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS. It should not make decisions itself with respect to\nthe number of units available in the NZ ETS, or its implementation."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\n\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI think expertise in public health is also important."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes. This may require a separate adaptation sub-committee within the Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The government passing an ambitious Zero Carbon Act is of the highest level of importance for the next generation. In 2050 I will be\n56 and will hopefully have children of my own roughly my own age. I want to be able to share with them the magic of Aotearoa as I\nhave been privileged enough to grow up in. For water to be clean to drink. For Oceans to be safe to swim in. I want for our native\n\nanimals to have an abundant habitat to inhabit and for them to be safe from extinction. For example the Tuatara will become all males\nif there is a rise in temperature as their sex is determined by the temperature at birth and we will loose a species that is millions of\n\nyears old. I don't want these animals to be something I show my children in books. This is New Zealanders chance to join in the\nsolution in a strong way. Lets make a law that we can be proud to tell our grandchildren about.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
